The new king of AI coding is here.
Enthropic just released Claude Sonnet
4.5 and it is looking really, really
good. I know that benchmarks don't tell
us the entire story, but right now
Sonnet 4.5 is at the top of the charts,
even beating out previous anthropic
models like Opus 4.1, and it is
apparently better than GBT codecs from
OpenAI, which has been absolutely
crushing it recently. Now, the big
question is, is it actually better in
practice? And so I'm going to be testing
live with you in this video, building
out the exact same implementation with
both Sonnet 4.5 in Cloud Code and GPT5
codecs in codecs. So more on that in a
little bit. Really excited for that. And
then for our other benchmarks, Sonnet
4.5 is now leading in aentic tool use.
And compared to Opus 4.1, we have some
massive strides in computer use. Almost
a 20% jump, which is really exciting.
Definitely a lot more with computer use
coming in the near future here. Now, we
also have the official Claude Code
version 2.0. So, a lot of improvements
they've made with Claude Code, of
course, being powered by Sonnet 4.5 by
default now. And you can still switch to
the old Opus 4.1 if you want. They also
added a VS Code extension. And they've
been making improvements to their Claude
Code SDK, which they're now calling the
Claude agents SDK. So if you want to
build custom agentic experiences using
cloud code, this is the ticket for you.
So yeah, a lot of improvements that
they've been making across the board.
Anthropic has been pumping out a ton of
content on their YouTube channel today.
So they're going hard with their new
Sonnet 4.5. And so with that, let's
actually do a test here. I want to see
how Sonnet 4.5 compares to GPT5 codecs
when working on a new feature in an
existing complex codebase. All right,
take a look at this. On the left side,
I've got codeex running with GBT5 codecs
for the LLM. And then for Cloud Code on
the right hand side, I'm running the
shiny new Sonnet 4.5. And I'm actually
really curious what the results of this
test is because I'm running this live
with you. I did not do a dry run of this
and a lot of people have been switching
over to codecs from Claude Code and so
I'm really curious if Sonnet 4.5 is
enough to bring everyone back. And I
know that one single test really isn't
enough to tell, but I'm just trying to
get my feet wet here with you, seeing
what kind of results that we get.
Executing on the exact same requirements
document that I have to build a Stripe
integration into an existing agentic
application. And so this is one of the
applications that I have built out for
the Dynamis community. It's a chat GBT
like interface to talk to a rag agent
behind the scenes. So I'm just giving a
really simple demo here. And I already
have the Stripe integration built out in
a different branch in Git. But yeah, we
can buy our tokens here. So I can go in
and enter in a fake credit card
information because this is just using
the Stripe test account here. So I
thought this is just going to be a
really nice demo for comparing our two
models now. So I'll go ahead and buy
some tokens here just so you can see how
this works exactly. I can go to my chat
here and now I have my updated token
balance and then when I send in another
message, it deducts the tokens
automatically. So this is like a little
overview of what we're looking to build
here with both cloud code and codeex.
And I picked this use case specifically
because it's not trivial, but it's also
not going to take 2 hours for this
implementation to complete. It's the
perfect balance here where generally
I've seen claude sonnet 4 mess up on the
little things but still mostly get it
right. And so we can see how that
compares now with GBT 5 codecs and
sonnet 4.5. So without further ado,
let's go ahead and kick off the
instruction set for both of our coding
agents. And so they're both working on a
different version of the repositories.
They're not stepping on each other's
toes. And also they're working on
something that is pre-stripe
integration. So this is the goal that
we're working towards that I demoed
earlier. They're working on a codebase
that doesn't have this whole thing set
up yet. So we'll go ahead and see how
they perform. And I'll just show you
really quickly the instruction set
they're working with here. So I've
showed PRPs on my channel before. It's
basically just a structured approach to
define our AI coding workflow. And so
the command that we just executed, it's
going to load our feature requirement,
think through the implementation, break
it down into tasks, and then handle that
task by task. That's what we're
executing right now in both codeex and
claude code. And so I'll pull up both of
these again. I'll go ahead and pause the
video and then come back once we have
the first attempt for both our coding
agents and we'll see the results. All
right, I'm back mid execution because I
want to show you how things are going in
cloud code and codeex while we are in
the middle of building the application.
So we've got codeex on the lefth hand
side doing a lot of stuff with the
database right now. It is failing to run
a lot of these commands which is not
looking the best for codecs and it's a
lot slower to do things like read
through my files in general. Claude
sonnet 4.5 on the other hand has been
blazing through this implementation.
Now, in the end, what matters the most
is code quality, but speed is nice as
well. And it definitely seems like
Sonnet is really, really fast,
especially with new 4.5. And then going
into Archon here, we can see the task
list for both Codex and Claude Code.
Claude has gotten through quite a bit
already. So, it just finished the
front-end purchase components for Stripe
for the tokens. Now, it's working on the
display components. And then Codeex,
they just finished the database schema
changes. Now, working on some of the
backend stuff with Stripe. So, they're
both chugging along pretty well.
Definitely a difference in speed though
here. So, I'll come back again once we
have the full implementation. We'll see
who knocked it out of the park the best.
There we go. Cloud code with Sonnet 4.5
has finished the implementation and it
did it in 15 minutes. The entire Stripe
implementation. It was very, very
impressive. I actually did this exact
same build with Opus 4.1 in the past and
it took 35 minutes to build the whole
thing. So more than two times faster now
with 4.5. Now I verified the output
before I even ran anything. I knew it
made a couple of mistakes, just small
things with the URLs between the front
end and the back end. So I had to
correct that. So it wasn't quite a
oneshot, but it was really, really
close. So I set up my environment and
restarted my containers here. So now we
have the same application that we saw
earlier, but instead of the previous one
that I built with Opus 4.1, this is the
version now built with a Sonnet 4.5.
Take a look at this. The UI is pretty
nice. Maybe it could be a little bit
better in the top right here, but still
pretty good. And I send in a message. I
don't have any tokens yet. Please
purchase more to continue. So I'll go
ahead and buy some tokens. And instead
of buying in line, it actually brings me
to a Stripe checkout here. I don't
really know which one's necessarily
better, but I mean this is certainly a
good implementation as well. So, I have
my test stripe running here. So, I'll
just go ahead and enter in some fake
credit card information. Again, have to
enter in a little bit more cuz it's a
checkout here. There we go. All right.
Pay for my tokens in the sandbox
environment. And boom, there we go.
Current tokens 250. Go back to chatting.
And now I'll send in a message just
hello for a quick test and see if we get
a response. There we go. All right, how
can I assist you today? It looks like
the token count did not update though.
So, if I refresh my page, now it goes
249. So, a little bit of an issue there.
Looks like I just have to iterate one
more time to make everything perfect.
But yeah, that's just two iterations and
we have this full Stripe integration
built into Claude Code. And meanwhile,
Codeex is still going. this entire time
as I did some updates even to like fix
up the URLs and stuff. Codeex has been
going for over a half hour now. And so
I'm going to pause again and come back
once codeex is done. But so far it's
really really disappointing me.
Actually, it looks like it's been going
for almost an hour now because I gave it
a lot of time. I took a break in between
Claude being done and me doing these
little fixes here and re-recording this.
And so yeah, it's been going on for over
an hour. So, Codeex seems pretty
disappointing here. Sonnet 4.5 is doing
a really good job. All right, I finally
got Codeex to finish. It took 1 hour and
20 minutes in total for the
implementation while Sonnet 4.5 took 15
minutes. So, the speed pretty
disappointing. It seemed to do a lot of
weird things where like after it would
edit a file, it would reread the file to
make sure the changes were made. things
like that that again might be specific
to codecs running on Windows, but I
really wasn't happy with that. So
anyway, I did the same thing with cloud
code where I gave it a couple of
chances. I iterated a couple of times
with some similar issues it had around
environment setup. This time more with
some Docker things specifically. So I
got that all squared away. I have the
containers running in Codeex again. And
so let's go back over to the site and
take a look at what we got. So first
thing that I noticed, the UI isn't quite
as nice. I mean, it'd be easy to fix
that. So, that's totally fine. Let's see
if we can purchase our tokens. So,
purchase tokens. Okay, looking really
good. And we even have a token history.
Doesn't seem to be perfect here, but
it's definitely cool that we have that.
So, let's go ahead. I'll purchase $20
worth of tokens here. I'll select this
and okay, nice. I think I do actually
prefer this than going to a separate
checkout page. So, so far the actual
results with using Codeex is pretty
good. I hate how long I had to wait, but
I mean it did a pretty good job with the
implementation. Things aren't perfect
yet. Like the transaction history and
the UI, but it's still pretty solid.
Yeah, there we go. Payment successful.
We have 600 tokens. The current balance
isn't quite right because that's
actually my old balance. So, things to
be improved here. But yeah, our token
balance is updated. I can send in a
message here and it'll deduct a token
from our agent. I might have to refresh
the page for it to refresh here. Okay.
So yeah, not quite perfect there either.
So there's like three or four issues
that we have to fix here. So not quite
as good of an implementation as cloud
code. This is why this is the perfect
use case cuz it's not trivial. We see
these problems as it messes up on
things, but also like it does a good
enough job where we can have a full
presentation demonstrating the mistakes
versus just the application crashing,
right? So yeah, this is pretty good. And
I can go in and reset my tokens down to
zero and we can make sure that we are
not able to send a message. Yep. Okay.
So, this is working really good. So,
overall, I would say that Claude Sonnet
4.5 was faster by a lot and better by a
decent amount. Codeex is still really
solid and I do think that we're going to
get to a point really quick where it
will catch up to Claude Code. However,
with Sonnet 4.5, they're definitely
winning the race right now. So, I hope
that you found this comparison
interesting. Very exciting what we've
got happening right now with Sonnet 4.5
continuing to push the LLM race further.
So, if you appreciated this video and
you're looking forward to more things on
large language models and building
agents and AI coding, I would really
appreciate a like and a subscribe. And
with that, I will see you in the next